Guide to the Montana Highway Planning Survey Records 1933-1963
Montana Historical Society
Montana Highway Planning Survey Records
1933-1963
Montana Historical Society Archives
RS 85
Montana Highway Planning Survey
.5 linear feet of shelf space
These Montana Highway Planning Survey records (1933-1963) consist of general correspondence, arranged by subject; subject files; and miscellany. (Maps and printed material transferred to Library.)
The Planning Survey of the State Highway Commission was established in 1936, jointly financed by the state and the U.S. Bureau of Public Roads. Also known as the Planning Survey Division, it was charged with developing any and all types of data that would be beneficial for highway planning. In order to fulfill that responsibility the Division was structured into three principal sections: Traffic, Mapping, and Statistics. The Traffic Section was given the responsibility of collecting data concerning the movement of motor vehicles on state highways, county roads, and city streets. The data was collected by means of both permanent and portable counters, as well as by visual counts and classifications. In addition to traffic counting, the Traffic Division was given a number of other functions including the weighing of trucks to obtain statistical information; the reporting of the number of accidents by location, type of accident, and economic cost; special urban transportation surveys for cities; origin destination surveys; and parking surveys. The Mapping Section was to prepare state highway maps, county maps, and city plats. The Mapping Section was also to collect data concerning county roads and to maintain a continuing inventory of all such roads in each county, including the type of surface of each road as well as mileages. The Mapping Section also performed special drafting of charts, graphs, and special exhibits. The Statistical Section was responsible for the compilation and reporting of a variety of financial and statistical data pertaining to highways, roads, and streets throughout Montana. These data were reported in published format and were also included in the summaries prepared by the U.S. Bureau of Public Roads for all states. The name of the Montana Highway Planning Survey was changed in 1966 to the Planning Survey Section, and, in 1971 following the statewide reorganization, became the Planning and Research Bureau under the new Department of Higlaways.
These records consist of general correspondence (1935-1963) arranged alphabetically by subject; printed material (1938-1939); subject files (1936-1945), arranged alphabetically; and miscellany. Maps and printed material have been transferred to the Library Map Collection and Library respectivelly.
The collection is arranged by series.
Collection open for research.
Acquisition information is available upon request.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Highway planning--Montana; Road surveying--Montana
Transportation; Montana
Detailed Description of the Collection
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection
- General correspondence
  - Administration BPR (re Bureau of Public Roads), 1955 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
  - Economic analysis, 1961-1963 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
  - Traffic, 1944-1963 (Box-folder 1 / 3)
  - Traffic: signs, 1935-1941 (Box-folder 1 / 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1936-1944 (Box-folder 1 / 5)
- Maps and printed material
  - Public Roads; list of maps and printed material transferred to Library Map collection and Library respectively, undated (Box-folder 1 / 6)
- Subject files
  - Key stations and blanket count stations, 1938-1939 (Box-folder 1 / 7)
  - Manuals of instruction, 1936 (Box-folder 1 / 8)
  - Method of expansion of Montana traffic data; Montana Highway Planning survey, 1938-1939 (Box-folder 1 / 9)
  - Traffic general - primary system; traffic general- secondary, 1940-1945 (Box-folder 1 / 10)
  - Truck and bus: general, 1936 (Box-folder 1 / 11)
  - Truck and bus: blanket count (part III), 1936 (Box-folder 1 / 12)
  - Truck and bus: key count (part IV), 1936 (Box-folder 1 / 13)
  - Truck and bus: loadometer stations (part V), 1936 (Box-folder 1 / 14)
  - Truck and bus: pit scale stations (part VI), 1936 (Box-folder 1 / 15)
- Miscellany
  - Blank forms, 1936-1937, undated (Box-folder 1 / 16)
  - Contracts let in 1932 and uncompleted on Mar. 30, 1933 (Box-folder 1 / 17)
  - Montana Highway Employees' Benefit Association bylaws, undated (Box-folder 1 / 18)
  - Portable counter plans; Folsom portable counter diagram, 1941 (Box-folder 1 / 19)
  - Traffic at state entrances: traffic profiles and maximum load study (US 310, US 10A, Park Cutoff), 1940 (Box-folder 1 / 20)
  - Traffic station locations, 1953 (Box-folder 1 / 21)
  - Weighing station reports (includes blank forms), 1952-1960 (Box-folder 1 / 22)
  - Western Association of State Highway Officials uniform code, 1938 (Box-folder 1 / 23)